Guide to the United Telegraph Workers Records WAG.144
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Telegraph Workers Records
1928-1996
1940-1986
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Telegraph Workers
Communications Workers of America / United Telegraph Workers Bargaining Council
WAG.144
45.5 Linear Feet in 45 record cartons and 10 folders.
The United Telegraph Workers, known until 1968 as the Commercial Telegraphers Union of America, emerged from a series of struggles between smaller unions of private and postal telegraph workers. Pitted against a single dominant employer, Western Union, and beset by technological change in the industry, the union declined in numbers after World War II. In 1986 it merged with the Communications Workers of America. The collection includes records of predecessor and rival unions, correspondence, bargaining files, bulletins, convention records, legal files, photographs, charters, and badges.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Communications Workers of America / United Telegraph Workers Bargaining Council in 1995. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1995.018, 1995.019 and NPA.1995.012. An additional donation of 19 boxes of Arbitration Appeals and Negotiations Records (Series X) was made circa 2005.
The accession number NPA.2001.019 is also associated with this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Western Union telegrams form a part of every archival collection in the country. What remains little known is the history of the workers who were employed in this industry, their working conditions, and their struggles for collective bargaining. The New York City Child Labor Committee inspected only thirteen telegraph offices in the entire metropolitan area (Manhattan alone contained 390 such offices). Managers freely admitted that the minimum working day for all boys was ten hours. In 1910, the New York State legislature passed the Murray Night Messenger Law, which barred minors under twenty one from engaging in night messenger work between the hours of 10:00 p.m. and 5:00 a.m. Not until 1934 did the law extend to all cities in the state. Meanwhile, the adults in the industry were left to their own devices to contest the monopoly power of their employers.
The telegraph and the railroad were in the vanguard of the transformation of America in the nineteenth century, and grew up together. The economy of speed offered by telegraphy was indispensable. Wire and rail often shared the same right of way. The Western Union Telegraph Company, founded in 1830, was the most important of all the many companies in the field. By 1878 Western Union had 7,672 offices, with 12,224 employees, and 199,022 miles of wire. The Baltimore & Ohio, its largest competitor, had 136 offices, 341 employees, and 1,409 miles of wire. The B&O was absorbed by Western Union in 1887. The Postal Telegraph Company was organized in the early 1880's, but it was and remained the junior partner.
Western Union's Board of Directors included Jay Gould, his son George, Collis Huntington, Russell Sage, Cyrus W. Field, C. Vanderbilt and J. P. Morgan. The company was organized along military lines, with a chain of command and territorial blocks (called divisions). Company headquarters was in New York City at 195 Broadway and it maintained a chain of "principal main offices" nationwide.
While telegraphy was eventually automated with the introduction of the teletypewriter, in the late nineteenth century it remained a skilled craft. As Western Union came to dominate the industry, operators' standing diminished, duties narrowed, and pay checks grew smaller. Western Union Rule Books dictated personal and work rules for its employees, but the Books never included seniority, salary, grievances, or any calculations for indications of skill or advancement.
In response, telegraphers made various efforts to organize collectively. The first national effort came in 1863, when operators met in New York City to form the National Telegraphic Union. Motions to include the clerks and cashiers, as well as the female operators, were defeated. In 1883, a national strike was organized by the Brotherhood of Telegraphers, part of the Knights of Labor. The Brotherhood was no match for its employers. The company subjected returning strikers to harassment and humiliation.
In 1885, the Telegraphers' Union of America was organized. And in 1886, railroad men formed the Order of Railway Telegraphers (O. R. T.), modelled along the lines of the conservative railroad brotherhoods. In June 1902, a new organization was formed, spurred on by many grievances. Each of the competing organizations appealed to the American Federation of Labor for a charter. A meeting was called in Pittsburgh, for all commercial telegraphers. Out of this two organizations emerged, both with charters from the AFL. Finally, on July 19, 1903, the two groups met in Washington, DC and merged to form one organization. The first convention was then held in New York City on July 20, 1903; on the twentieth anniversary of the Great Strike of 1883, the Commercial Telegraphers' Union (CTU) was born. One hundred delegates represented seventy-five locals from across the country. Separate departments were established for the press and brokerage houses, as well as for commercial telegraphy. When the union presented a "bill of grievances" to the President of Western Union, the company's intransigence eventually led to a national strike. Operators across the country were discharged for union activity. The strike was lost. Postal Telegraph employees participated in the strike. Now Postal Telegraph formed an association of its employees to forestall further unionization.
Buffalo, New York was the location for the CTU's 6th annual convention. The union officials' rooms were entered, and union records, including a list of 1,700 members' names, were stolen. Firings across the country followed; special agents were hired by Western Union to track down members and to disrupt union activity. Meanwhile, a national Committee on Industrial Relations was investigating conditions in the industry, uncovering many abuses. The War Labor Board, established by President Wilson to handle labor disputes during World War I, eventually led to the formation of a company union or "association." The Association Western Union Employees (sic, AWUE) came into being almost overnight. Bargaining rights were immediately granted to an organization without members. The AWUE stipulated that its members could not also be members an AFL union, and promotions and pay raises were preferentially granted to those who belonged to the company union. By the end of its first year, the AWUE had enlisted 20,000 members out of a possible 40,000. At its peak in 1930, 38,603 Western Union employees were members of the AWUE.
The 1930's were a period of intense conflict and rivalry within the communications industry and the unions which sought to represent the workers in the developing technologies. One of the most significant for the future history of the CTU was the organization of the American Radio Telegraphists Association (which changed its name to the American Communications Association in 1937). The ACA won an NLRB election among the Postal Telegraph workers in 1937. Postal Telegraph and Western Union merged in 1943. Now the competition between ACA and CTU for the right to represent Western Union workers accelerated. In 1938, the ACA filed unfair labor practices against Western Union for coercing its employees against joining the union and for fostering a company union. In 1939, Western Union was found guilty and ordered to "cease and desist." The campaign to organize the Western Union workers now took off, with assistance from the CIO for the ACA, and the AFL for the CTU.
In November 1944, the NLRB ordered seven elections for Western Union to take place in January 1945. A major issue was made of Communist influence, and charges against Joseph Selly, president of the ACA, were widely circulated by his rivals. The CTU won six out of seven divisions. The ACA won the right to represent the Metropolitan Division in New York City. Thus was born a long and bitter enmity. A National Bargaining Agency was brokered and set up to bargain for all. A national agreement was signed in 1945, with president W. L Allen signing for the CTU and president William Green for the AFL.
Between 1946 and 1949, Western Union's message business declined by sixteen percent. President Truman appointed a Policy Board to study the problem. Their 1951 report found that the lessening of demand for telegram service and technological changes threatened the existence of the Western Union system as a private enterprise. Advances in automation also took a toll on the membership of the union. A few large central exchanges and computer centers took over services formerly handled by small offices across the country.
Teletype and data exchange systems for government and private enterprise were maintained by CTU/UTW members. The country's first transcontinental microwave system, with communications over Western Union's satellite, WESTAR, the first commercial communications satellite in the world, was also maintained by UTW members. Ultimately, changes in technology dictated changes in the structure of the union. The merger of the UTW with the Communications Workers of America in 1986 led to the formation of the CWA/UTW Bargaining Council.
Sources:
Dunn, Robert W. Company Unions: Employers' Industrial Democracy. New York: Vanguard Press, 1927.
Gabler, Edwin. The American Telegrapher: A Social History, 1860 1900. New Brunswick: Rutgers University Press, 1988.
Kravif, Hy. The Telephone and Telegraph Workers. New York: International Pamphlets No. 44, 1935.
Sanders, Donald G. The Brass Pounder. New York: Hawthorn Books, 1978.
Silva, Anthony J. "The Compliant Agent: The Road to Company Unionism in the Telegraph." Master of Arts Thesis in History, Sonoma State University, 1991.
Thompson, Robert Luther. Wiring a Continent: The History of the Telegraph Industry in the United States. 1832-1866. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1974.
Ulriksson, Vidkunn. The Telegraphers: Their Craft and Their Unions. Washington, D.C.: Public Affairs Press, 1953.
Government Printing Office, Washington, D.C. Investigation of Western Union and Postal Telegraph Cable Companies. 1909.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Records of the Communications Workers of America.
United Telegraph Workers appeal cases can be found on microfilm. See the listing in the NYU library catalog: http://www.bobcat.nyu.edu:1701/primo_library/libweb/action/display.do?fn=display&doc=nyu_aleph003340789&vid=NYU&persistent
Scope and Content Note
The United Telegraph Workers Records includes records of predecessor and rival unions, correspondence, national office bulletins, convention proceedings and resolutions, election materials, organizational and industry histories, articles of agreement, contracts, arbitrations, legal documents, collective bargaining and strike materials, materials related to the Joint Labor Management Task Force and Quality of Work Life Program, photographs, badges and charters. Materials date from 1928 to 1996.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in 11 series. Folders are generally arranged chronologically within each series. The series arrangement of the records is as follows:
I, History and Jurisdictional Disputes
II, Internal Structure and Divisions of the CTU/UTW
III, Correspondence
IV, Bulletins
V, Convention Proceedings
VI, Indexed Arbitrations
VII, Collective Bargaining Materials
VIII, Joint Labor-Management Task Force/Quality of Work Life
IX, Subsidiaries Case
X, Arbitration Appeals and Negotiations XI, Photographs, Badges, and Charters
Clippings (information artifacts); Collective bargaining |x Telegraphers.; Telegraphers.; Correspondence.; Labor unions -- United States.; Telegraph |x Employees.; Telegraphers |x Labor unions.; Newsletters.; Photographs.; Records (documents); United Telegraph Workers; Hageman, E. L.; Beckstead, D. J.; American Communications Association; Association Western Union Employees; Commercial Telegraphers' Union of America; Western Union Telegraph Company; Communications Workers of America / United Telegraph Workers Bargaining Council
- Series I: History & Jurisdictional Disputes
  Scope and Content Note
  Series includes histories of the CTU, and the Association Western Union Employees, brief histories of technology and the technological changes that affected the telegraph industry; and materials relating to the various organizations which were competing for membership in the telegraph industry. Includes election materials, War Labor Board and National Labor Relations Board cases; arbitrations, articles of agreement, mergers and amalgamation agreements.
  - Constitution, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - History, 1928-1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - History, 1928-1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - History, 1928-1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - History, 1928-1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - History, 1928-1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - History, 1928-1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - History Telegraph, 1928-1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - AFL v. CIO (CTU/Radio Officers Union (ROU)/American; Communications Association (ACA), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Association Western Union Employees (AWUE) Assembly; (Boston, Mass), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Western Union (Western Union) election (Atlanta, Georgia); Telegraph Employees Union, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Western Union Division established (Articles of Agreement), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - CTU AFL and Telegraph Employees (Federal) Union; (Agreement), 1943-1948 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - AFL v. ACA (CTU/ROU), 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Anti ACA campaign literature, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Western Union ACA hearing; National War Labor Board (transcript), Dec 30, 1943Apr 24, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - AFL v. ACA; Election NLRB, 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Election, NLRB; AFL v. ACA (CTU), Sept. '46 May '47, 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - ACA Western Union Arbitration, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - ACA Western Union 1950, 1966 (Articles of Agreement; correspondence) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Western Union/Postal Telegraph merger; 1943 (FCC) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Western Union/Postal Telegraph merger (printed; documents/information), 1943 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - National War Labor Board; Arbitration (Western Union (Western Union)/Postal merger; Western Union ACA TEU merger), 1944 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - AFL Western Union agreement, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - CTU charters to Western Union Employees Union; Western Union Telegraph; Union (Amalgamation Agreement), 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Merger Agreement Western Union Federal Unions (National Bargaining; Committee), 1949 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Contract Western Union AFL, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Amalgamation Agreement (Telegraph Workers), 1951 (Box 1, Folder 29(a))
  - Western Union Commercial Telegraphers Union (CTU) Re organization effort, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Series II: Internal Structure and Divisions of the CTU/UTW
  Series includes materials related to the structure, the numerous reorganization plans, and records relating to the various divisions within the union. These include the Southern, Southwestern, and Western Union Divisions, the Canadian Pacific Division and the Press Divisions, representing the Associated Press (A.P.) And the United Press International (U.P.I.). Materials include correspondence, election, bargaining and strike materials.
  - Western Union/CTU Re organization effort, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Western Union/CTU Re organization effort, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Re organization (1955 1957 Proposed re organization and; opposition; correspondence) (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Re organization (proposed), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Re organization (proposal), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence 1955, proposed re organization, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Amalgamation agreement, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Re organization CTU Western Union (merger Southern and Western; Divisions), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Re organization (CTU October 18, 1965 consolidated into one; Unit) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - So. Division, October 3 4 (merger of So. and West. Divs., CTU), 1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - CTU/merger Western Union Division, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - CTU Western Union (proposed merger), 1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Merger Southern, Southwestern and Western Union Divs., 1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - merger #2 Southern, Southwestern, Western Union Divs., 1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Merger Agreements; 1968; 1969; Southern and Southwestern Divs., 1928-1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - CTU Name change (proposed), 1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Merger talks #1; continued negotiations (February October), 1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - #2 (February October 1985); (November '85 January'86) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Div. 1, Div. 43 (Canadian Pacific); CTU Correspondence (arbitration, attorney's fees), 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - CTU Canadian Pacific Division #1; (Amended) By laws, 1928-1996 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Div. #1 Canadian Pacific; Div. #43 CTU Correspondence 1968 (contracts; other) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Div. #1/#43 Canadian Pacific CTU; Correspondence, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Div. #1/#43 Canadian Pacific CTU; Correspondence, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Div. #1/#43 Canadian Pacific/CTU/UTW; Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Div. #1/#43 Canadian Pacific UTW; Correspondence, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - United Press International (UPI) Div. #47; Correspondence, contracts, negotiations, by laws, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Div. #14 Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Div. #14 Associated Press (AP) "Chapel Chatter" (December '67; December'68), 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - UTW Div. #14 AP; Correspondence, notes, Bulletins, draft contract, 1928-1996 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - UTW Div. #14 AP; Correspondence, notes, Bulletins, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - UTW Div. #14 Arbitration (Brief), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - UTW Div. #14 Contract negotiations, notes, Bulletins, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - NLRB; strike flyer, stickers, 1928-1996 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - UTW Div. #14 AP; Disaffiliation Div. # 14 UTW CWA affiliation/merger, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Series III: Correspondence
  Series includes the Presidents' correspondence, Executive Board correspondence, and correspondence of the divisions. This section includes only those materials from the E. L. Hageman and D. J. Beckstead administrations.
  - International President's Correspondence; E.L. Hageman, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - International President's Correspondence; E.L. Hageman, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - International President's Correspondence; E.L. Hageman, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - International President's Correspondence; E.L. Hageman, Jan 1971-Oct 1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - International President's Correspondence; D.J. Beckstead, Nov 1971-Dec 1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - International President's Correspondence; D.J. Beckstead, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - International President's Correspondence; D.J. Beckstead, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - International President's Correspondence; D.J. Beckstead, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - International President's Correspondence; D.J. Beckstead, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - International President's Correspondence WUBRISA Pension revisions, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - International President's Correspondence; D.J. Beckstead, 1977, 1978, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - IEB Correspondence #1, Jan 1965-Apr 1966 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - IEB Correspondence #2, May 1966-Dec 1966 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - IEB Correspondence #1, Jan 1967-Apr 1967 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - IEB Correspondence #2, May 1967-Dec 1967 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - IEB Correspondence, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - TEB Correspondence, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - IEB Correspondence, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Board of Trustees So. Div. Western Union correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Div. #47 United Press (B.C. Red Appeal), 1928-1996 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Div. #47; (Appeal; Election of Officers, 1948-1952 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Div. #43; Western Dist. CTU (correspondence, overtime dispute), 1945 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Div. #61 Appeal;; William Howard Harris, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Appeal #61, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - DuPont, Organizing Drive, CTU, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - The CTU Leader Local 146, NYC, Mar 1957 (Box 3, Folder 25(a))
  - General correspondence (includes Taft Hartley), 1940-1983 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - PTTI (Postal, Telegraph and Telephone International); correspondence, programs, CWA convention, 1928-1996 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Western Union News: April 15, 1968; March 12, 1973; August 1973 January; 1976; Western Union News: January 21, 1953 Reperforator: 1963, E.L. Hageman, 1953-1973 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - CTU Letterhead, 1928-1996 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Series IV: Bulletins
  Issued by the national office, the collection includes bulletins from 1959 to 1989.
  - Bulletins' CTU/LJTW Western Union Div., 1959 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bulletins, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bulletins, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Bulletins, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Bulletins, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Bulletins, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Bulletins, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Bulletins, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Bulletins, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Bulletins, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Bulletins, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Bulletins, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Bulletins, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Bulletins, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Bulletins, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Bulletins, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Bulletins, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Bulletins, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Bulletins, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Bulletins, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Bulletins, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Bulletins, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Bulletins, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Bulletins, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Bulletins, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Bulletins, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Series V: Convention Proceedings
  The proceedings date from 1928 (the 14th Regular Convention) and end with 1994's Special Convention. The CTU Western Union Division Convention Proceedings follow, beginning with 1942 and ending in 1975. The materials include typescript proceedings, reports, miscellaneous documents..
  - CTU Convention proceedings; Vol. I (14th Reg. Convention), 1928 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - CTU Convention proceedings; Vol. H (14th Reg. Convention), 1928 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - CTU Convention (18th Reg. Convention); proceedings, officers reports, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - CTU Convention (19th Reg. Convention); proceedings, officers reports, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - CTU Convention (20th Reg. Convention); proceedings, officers reports, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - CTU Convention (21 st Reg. Convention); proceedings, officers reports, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - CTU Convention (22nd Reg. Convention); proceedings, officers reports, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - CTU Convention (23rd Reg. Convention); proceedings, officers reports, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - CTU Convention; 23rd Reg. Convention, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - CTU Convention Book Vol. 11, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - CTU Convention (24th Reg. Convention) proceedings, officers reports, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - CTU Convention (25th Reg. Convention) proceedings, officers reports, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - CTU Convention (26th Reg. Convention) proceedings, officers reports, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - CTU Convention (27th Reg. Convention) proceedings, officers reports, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 14)